Guide to the Leroy J. Robertson music recordings 1920s-1970s
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Leroy J. Robertson music recordings
1920s-1970s
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0241
Robertson, Leroy J.
Phonograph records and reel-to-reel audiotapes
The Leroy J. Robertson music recordings (1920s-1970s) consist of audio recordings of pieces composed by Robertson as well as other music including hymns, carols, classical music and compositions by other American composers, some of which Robertson conducted or arranged. A respected composer of works for chamber music, orchestra, violin, cello, piano and voice, Leroy J. Robertson taught music at Brigham Young University (BYU), the University of California Los Angeles (UCLA) and the University of Utah before retiring in 1964.
Biographical Note
Leroy J. Robertson (1896-1971) was born in Fountain Green, Utah, on 21 December 1896, the son of Utah-born Mormon parents. His first musical experiences were simple and personal--he fashioned tunes on a homemade fiddle and played by ear on the parlor organ in his home. In grammar school, after a few rudimentary music lessons, he organized a small orchestra of young friends and taught them to play music of his own devising. He graduated from the New England Conservatory of Music in boston under George Whitefield Chadwick in 1923. His later studies were under Ernest Bloch in San Francisco and in Roveredo Capriasca, Switzerland; Hugo Leichtentritt in Berlin; and Arnold Schoenberg in Los Angeles. He received his B.A. and M.A. degrees from Brigham Young University (BYU) and Ph.D. degree from the University of Southern California, Los Angeles. He was professor and chairman of the music department at BYU; lecturer of composition at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) and professor and chairman of the music department at the University of Utah from 1948 until his retirement in 1964. Upon retirement, Robertson received the first Distinguished Research Professorship at that institution.
Robertson was an honorary member of Phi Beta Kappa; a fellow of the Utah Academy of Arts, Sciences, and Letters; a member of the Executive Music Committee of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints; and a member of the American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishrs (ASCAP). Robertson's compositions include works for chamber music and orchestra; concertos for violin, cello, and piano; solos, vocal, and instrumental; choral compositions and an "Oratorio from the Book of Mormon" for chorus, soloists, organ, and orchestra. While the Reichhold prize for his "Trilogy" was by far the most impressive, Robertson has a long list of other awards to hs credit. In 1923, he won the Endicott prize for his "Overture in E Minor"; his "Quintet in A Minor for Piano and Strings" won first place in a contest conducted by the Society for Publicaiton of American Music in 1936; his "String Quartet" was chosen by the Critics Circle in New York in 1944; and his "Rhapsody for Piano and Orchestra" was given an award by the Utah Institute of Fine Arts in 1945. He received the National Federation of Music Clubs Award of Merit in 1959. Robertson died on 25 July, 1971 in Salt Lake City.
The Leroy J. Robertson music recordings (1920s-1970s) are phonograph records and reel-to-reel audiotapes of pieces composed by Robertson as well as other music including hymns, carols, classical music and compositions by other American composers, some of which Robertson conducted or arranged. Several pieces are performed by Utah musical groups including the Utah Symphony and the University of Utah Orchestra.
The materials are arranged by format. Most of the items in each format are listed alphabetically by title of composition.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
This collection is open to public research on library premises but no copies may be made.
See also the Leroy J. Robertson papers (Ms 38) and photograph collection (P0038). Sheet music for some of Robertson's compositions is available in the Maurice Abravanel papers (Ms 517).
Abravanel, Maurice, 1903-1993; American composers; Orchestral music; Music; Sound Recordings; Sound recordings
- American Serenade, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 1-2)
  Performed by Feri Roth with Normal Lee Madsen, Sally Peck and Marian Robertson.
- American Serenade, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 3-6)
  Performed by Utah Symphony Strings.
- American Serenade, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 7-8)
  Performed by the Roth Quartet
- American Serenade, Caprice, Nocturne, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 9)
  Performed by Roth, Madsen, Peck, and M. Robertson
  Recorded by the University of Utah Radio Committee.
- American Serenade test pressing, 1961; Phonograph record (Disc 10)
  Performed by the Weicher Quartet
- Fantasia for Organ, 1955; Phonograph record (Disc 11)
  Performed by Robert Cundick, organ.
- Novelette: Carl Fuerstner (piano), undated; Phonograph record (Disc 12)
- Oratorio from the Book of Mormon test pressing, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 13)
- Passacaglia, 1955; Phonograph record (Disc 14-17)
  Performed by the Utah Symphony Orchestra.
  Conductor: Maurice Abravanel
- Prelude, Scherzo and Ricercare parts 1-4, 1948; Phonograph record (Disc 18-19)
- Punch and Judy, 1951; Phonograph record (Disc 20)
  Performed by the National Broadcasting Company (NBC) Symphony Orchestra.
- Punch and Judy, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 21)
  Standard Hour NBC, Los Angeles
- Punch and Judy, 1949; Phonograph record (Disc 22)
- Quartet in E minor, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 23-24)
  Performed by the Roth Quartet.
- Quartet in E minor, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 25-26)
- Quartet in E minor, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 27)
- Quintet in A minor for piano and strings parts 1-4, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 28-29)
  Performed by the Roth Quartet and Carl Fuerstner, piano.
- Quintet in A minor for piano and strings part 5 and G minor Etude, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 30)
  G minor Etude performed by Reid Nibley, piano.
- Quintet in A minor for piano and strings, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 31-32)
  Performed by Ferli Roth, Harold Wolf, Sally Peck, Marian Robertson and Reid Nibley.
- Rhapsody for piano and orchestra, circa 1947; Phonograph record (Disc 33-34)
  Performend by Andor Foldes, piano.
  Conductor: Leon Barzin
  WABC boradcast
- Rhapsody for piano and orchestra parts 2-6, 1947; Phonograph record (Disc 35-36)
  Performend by the WCBS Symphony and Andor Foldes, piano.
  WCBS broadcast "Invitation to Music"
- Symphony no. 2, Trilogy, 1947; Phonograph record (Disc 37-38)
  Performed by the Utah Symphony.
- Symphony no. 2, Trilogy parts 1-2, 1957; Phonograph record (Disc 39)
- Symphony no. 2, Trilogy parts 1-3 (complete), 1947; Phonograph record (Disc 40-45)
  Performed by the Detroit Symphony Orchestra.
  Conductor: Karl Krueger
  World premiere with award presentation.
  Recorded from tapes.
- Concerto for violoncello, 1956; Phonograph record (Disc 46-47)
  Performed by the Utah Symphony Orchestra and Zara Nelsova, cello (entire concerto), Marian Robertson, cello, and Gladys Gladstone, piano (finale).
- Concerto for violoncello, 1956 (Disc 48-49)
  Performed by the Utah Symphony Orchestra and Zara Nelsova, cello, and Marian Robertson and Gladys Gladstone, piano.
- Fugue in C minor, 1952 (Disc 50)
  Performed by William L. Fowler and Robert Cundick, piano.
- Mozart's Sonata in G major and Robertson's Eb Etude, 1946 (Disc 51)
  Sonata in G major performed by Mary Kroll, violin, and Marian Robertson, piano.
  Eb Etude performed by Carl Fuerstner, piano.
- Latter-day Organist: hymns, preludes, postludes, undated (Disc 52)
  Performed by Alexander Schreiner, organ.
  Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (LDS) General Music Committee
- The Lord's Prayer and Battle Hymn of the Republic, 1949 (Disc 53)
  Performed by the South High School a cappella choir, Salt Lake City, Utah.
- Ernest Toch's Symphony no. 2, undated (Disc 54-55)
- Alleluia and Chorale, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 56-58)
  Performed by the University of Utah band.
- American Serenade, 1943; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 59-60)
- Book of Mormon Oratorio, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 61-64)
- Book of Mormon Oratorio (exerpts), 1958; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 65-66)
  Performed by the Summer Youth Chorus Program.
- Concerto for cello and orchestra, 1956; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 67-69)
  Performed by the Utah Symphony Orchestra and Zara Nelsova.
- University of Utah Festival Overture, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 70-71)
- Passacaglia, 1955; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 72-74)
- Passacaglia, 1959; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 75-77)
- Passacaglia, 1960; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 78-80)
- Piano Etudes, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 81)
- Piano Rhapsody, circa 1944; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 83)
  Performed by the Utah Symphony Orchestra and Andor Foldes, piano.
- Punch and Judy, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 86-90)
- Quintet for Piano and Strings, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 91-92)
  Performed by the Paganini Quartet and Wolman, piano.
- Saguaro Overture, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 93-95)
- Symphony no. 2, Trilogy, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 96-99)
- Brahms' Violin Concerto, slow movement, circa 1953; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 100)
  Performed by the University of Utah Symphony.
  Conductor: Leroy J. Robertson
- Delius' Walk to Paradise Garden and Wagner's Rienzi, circa 1953; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 101)
- Mendelssohn's Symphony no. 5 in D minor, circa 1953; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 102)
- Mozart's Violin Concerto (exerpts), undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 103)
  Performed by Harold Wolf and Ardean Watts
- Schumann'a 4th Symphony in D Major, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 104)
- Summer Youth Chorus, 1958; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 105)
  Performed with Alexander Schreiner, organ.
- Tchaikovsky's Symphony no. 6, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 106-107)
- Folk Songs Collection, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 108)
  Compiled by Dr. Cheney.
- O Little Town of Bethlehem, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 109)
  Arranged by Leroy J. Robertson.
  Performed by the Mormon Tabernacle Choir and the New York Philharmonic Orchestra.
  Conductor: Leonard Bernstein
- Selections from Verdi, Flowtow, Donizetti, Sibelius and Weber, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 110)